git is capable of automatically transforming line-endigs
one way to set it up this functionality is
core.autocrlf setting. It has 3 possible values.
The first one is 'true'. It is oriented mainly
towards Windows users.
If you installed git under Windows and left
default settings during the process
you do not have to change anything: your system
is already configured to use true. With this setting when
you save a text file in git, it is run through what is
called normalization: double Windows line-endings CR LF
are substituted by single Unix LF.
The transformed file is than stored by git.
And vice-versa: when we fetch a file from a git database
LF endings are substituted by CR LF. As a result
we end up with a kind of 2-way conversion. Inside the git
files are with LF line-endings, but when we work with them
we see Windows style CR LF line-endigs.
Now, if we use git to share
to share our files, those who work on Unix
systems would get our files
with LF line-endigs. And would be very happy.
And those who work on Windows
would also get the files with LF file endings,
but they most likely would have the same settings.
Hence, when the receive our files from the git storage,
their git instance would convert LF to CR LF.
I.e. they would see the files with native Windows line endings.
At the end of the day, every one is happy. Another option is called
'input'. Contrary to the previous one
input.
it does only one way conversion. I.e. when
we save a file in git, CR LF line endings are converted to LF
And when we receive a file from git, no conversion is done.
It is an excellent option for Unix systems because
on a Unix system a file with Windows line endings can appear
only accidentally. For instance someone could have
copied it directly from Windows bypassing git.
In this case the input setting would fix the issue.
I will note, that very often this option is chosen
by those who work on Windows in case
the main environment for their project remains Unix.
In this case, they setup their IDE to use LF
as line endings. Modern code editors allow to do it
quite easily. So, by choosing
this option, you tell git that the default line endings
in your project are LF, and CR LF
could appear in your files only by accident
and must be removed as quickly as possible. And, finally,
the last option is 'false' whicsh is set by default.
This options tells git to do nothing.
It is an excellent choice for when there is no problem with line endings.
For example, every team member works on a Unix system.
Or every one uses Windows.
And we know for sure that it will always be this way
and there will be no cross-platform development in the foreseeable future.
In this case every one has the same line endings and
we can leave everything as it is. Also this option is chosen
by orderly developers, who know for sure that their
code editors are setup correctly, that everything is ok with line endings,
and they do not want git to do any kind of automatic
conversion. At the same you should understand that
a file with CR LF endings would be saved to git
as is. So, if one of the developers
has autocrlf set up, and another one does not,
or has a 'false' option set up by error, then
we would end up with a line ending mess in our git repository:
some files would have LF, others - CR LF.
In order to avoid it, there are alternative ways to
setup git through attributes, which we will have a look at later.
This is all for the core.autocrlf.
But in order to fully understand what happens behind the scenes
we must answer one more important question:
in which files does git convert the line endings?
Obviously not in each one.
In git we can store all kinds of files, both text and binary.
But whilst we can replace line endings
for cross-platform development in text files,
an attempt to change bytes in binary file, let's say an image,
would simply break it and corrupt the data.
But how does git know if a given file
is text or binary?
Does it have a magic mirror?
Of cource not! May be by the file extension?
It could be set up to do so, but by default it does not.
It looks at the content.
At what exactly? Could git's method fail leading
to a situation in which a text file
is mistaken for binary, and vice-versa.
It is quite an important question because a
failure to correctly identify the file type could lead
to errors in line endings conversion. Or, in the case of a binary file,
to it's corruption.
Unfortunately documentation on the subject is scarce.
But here is what the git's source code has to say about this.
The corresponding function is quite short.
Git analyzes the content of the file and if it sees CR
Git
not followed by LF it assumes that the file is binary.
Indeed, Unix uses LF as line endigs,
Windows - CR LF.
And a CR not followed by LF would be strange for
a text file. Git decides that it must by binary.
Or, in the case the file has a null byte.
In general text files do not have it. So the file must be binary.
And, finally, git assumes that in text files there must
be 128 times more printable characters than there
are unprintable ones.
Therefore, if this proportion is violated, then the
file must be binary. If not - it must be a text file.
The logic is quite simple.
In practice it is quite robust, and while it could fail once
in a while, there is an explicit way to let git know
which files are text through
attributes. We will talk about it in one of the future screencasts.
For the future, so that there is no confusion, I will note,
that this function is used to distinguish text files from binary
files only for the purpose of line ending conversion.
There is a similar function in git
used for comparison, merging and other,
which simply checks if there is a single null byte
among the first 8 000 bytes.
If 'yes' - the file is binary, if 'not' - text.